<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.welltemperedclavier.org/preludes-and-fugues" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Preludes and Fugues</title>
    <link>https://www.welltemperedclavier.org/preludes-and-fugues</link>
    <description></description>
    <language>en</language>
     <atom:link href="https://www.welltemperedclavier.org/preludes-and-fugues.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
    <title>J.S. Bach’s Well-Tempered Clavier — A Video for the Curious</title>
    <link>https://www.welltemperedclavier.org/bach/js-bach%E2%80%99s-well-tempered-clavier%E2%80%8A%E2%80%94%E2%80%8A-video-curious-1</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;field field--body&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-item even&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bach’s music expresses joy, sorrow, excitement, and a profound beauty. But it is also very complex music, with many voices doing many things at the same time. Hearing and understanding everything that is going on is not straightforward, and it is not something that can be achieved just by listening, even after many repeat listenings. To fully comprehend how this music is crafted, it is necessary to read it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reading and listening to this Bach masterpiece just got easier with a new video that combines two open source scores with the piano playing of Kimiko Ishizaka to present you a complete performance of the Well-Tempered Clavier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Fugues, in particular, are quite special in this video. For each Fugue, the score separates the voices into their own lines, so you can see how all of them fit together. Take this example from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/nPHIZw7HZq4?t=1h32m26s&quot;&gt;5-voice Bb Minor Fugue&lt;/a&gt; to see how clearly the voices are shown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/nPHIZw7HZq4?t=1h32m26s&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.welltemperedclavier.org/sites/default/files/articles/files/fugue22_expanded.pdf-12-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Excerpt from Bach’s Fugue No. 22 in Bb Minor, BWV 867&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Excerpt from Bach’s Fugue No. 22 in Bb Minor, BWV 867&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two sources for scores were used. For the Preludes, the Open Well-Tempered Clavier score from Musescore was used. For the Fugues, the public domain engraving by Kyle Rother using Lillypond software was chosen. As a consequence, you can easily compare the default engraving styles of Musescore and Lillypond, side by side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The video is over one hour and forty-nine minutes long. Given that none of it repeats, and it is polyphonic throughout, that makes for some very dense listening (an attribute that you will grow to cherish as you build familiarity). But where to start, and how to listen if the music is totally new to you and you’re trying to get a toehold?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, a lot has been written about The Well-Tempered Clavier. A growing number of the pieces are discussed on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://welltemperedclavier.org/preludes-and-fugues&quot;&gt;Open Well-Tempered Clavier website&lt;/a&gt;. There is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3tU1PDS9kyI&quot;&gt;nice video from Dave Conservatoire&lt;/a&gt;, “What is a Fugue?” that features a performance of the C-Minor Fugue by Kimiko Ishizaka. Finally, there is an outstanding set of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www2.nau.edu/tas3/wtc.html&quot;&gt;analysis with illustrations and examples by Timothy A. Smith &lt;/a&gt;— highly recommended!&lt;br /&gt;
However, if you want to jump in and start listening here are some highlights to get you going.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Prelude in C Major (the first piece)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nPHIZw7HZq4&quot;&gt;a beloved favorite&lt;/a&gt;. Technically easy enough for many piano students to get through, its apparent simplicity hides the fact that the piece is a miracle of uniqueness. It defies all of the rules and norms of the day, and you can’t really find other pieces like it (unless they’re based on it).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Fugue in C Minor&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s a wonderful &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/nPHIZw7HZq4?t=6m26s&quot;&gt;example of a fugue&lt;/a&gt;, with three voices, and you can start to get a feel for the whole idea of a fugue, where an initial melody, or theme, is presented by each voice, offset by time and pitch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Eb Minor Prelude&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This piece will teach you the meaning of &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/nPHIZw7HZq4?t=30m21s&quot;&gt;sound colours on the piano&lt;/a&gt;. Listen to the repeated chords; each one sounds different from the previous, sometimes brighter, sometimes darker, always supporting the melancholic melodic lines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Ab Major Fugue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/nPHIZw7HZq4?t=1h11m30s&quot;&gt;Joy. Pure joy.&lt;/a&gt; Much of music history was spent being sad, with upbeat music only serving to exacerbate the fall into emotional disarray (e.g. the entire Romantic period.) Bach, however, was capable of unfettered rejoicing, and this fugue rejoices quite merrily.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The A Minor Fugue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/nPHIZw7HZq4?t=1h22m41s&quot;&gt;This is a monster&lt;/a&gt;. With four voices, the technical challenges to the pianist are enormous. What’s more impressive, however, is how Bach takes you on a whirlwind journey that ends big. Really really big.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Bb Minor Prelude&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The opposite of the Ab Major Fugue, i.e. no joy. None at all. Only &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/nPHIZw7HZq4?t=1h39m59s&quot;&gt;sadness, yearning, and desolation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The B Minor Fugue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are no words left for what Bach did with this. The fugue theme uses all 12 chromatic tones, and the resulting harmonies and structures as he develops that material are so inexplicable that music historians and analysts are left scratching their heads trying to explain how he created such &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/nPHIZw7HZq4?t=1h41m1s&quot;&gt;wondrous and radical music&lt;/a&gt;. Pay careful attention to the three magisterial sequences that punctuate the structure of the piece.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the full video. Enjoy, and share with those who love music.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;853&quot; height=&quot;480&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/nPHIZw7HZq4?showinfo=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 04 Dec 2015 11:50:51 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>Robert Douglass</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">39 at https://www.welltemperedclavier.org</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Prelude No 1 in C Major, BWV 846</title>
    <link>https://www.welltemperedclavier.org/bach/prelude-no-1-c-major-bwv-846</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;field field--body&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-item even&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;In it&#039;s whole, the Well-Tempered Clavier delves into some of the most complicated and compelling counterpoint ever written. For example, the piece that ends the cycle of Book 1, the great B-Minor Fugue, is so chromatic and convoluted that it shocks the modern ear with its complexity. At the start of the cycle, however, Bach bluffs us with &quot;simplicity&quot;. The C-Major Prelude, famous for its naive beauty, and for the fact that nearly every piano student takes a crack at it sometime in their studies, is actually an almost ironic outlier in a collection of polyphonic works. It is not immediately polyphonic (though it can be strongly argued that there are indeed five voices from start to finish), and it is even devoid of a theme. At first glance it is nothing but a series of arpeggiated chords around a nice, but not especially daring, harmonic progression in C Major. The subtle beauty of the music is undeniable, though, and it stands out through the whole of music history as distinctly recognisable and endearing, which is an excellent way to start off the monumental achievement of The Well-Tempered Clavier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;853&quot; height=&quot;480&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/87FGM0_3QZE?showinfo=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Sat, 15 Aug 2015 13:33:24 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>Robert Douglass</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">30 at https://www.welltemperedclavier.org</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Prelude No 1 in C Major, BWV 846 - VIDEO</title>
    <link>https://www.welltemperedclavier.org/bach/prelude-no-1-c-major-bwv-846-video</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;field field--body&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-item even&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;853&quot; height=&quot;480&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/3RBgy9q8wFg&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;p&gt;J.S. Bach, Prelude No 1 in C Major, BWV 846 - video by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC2zb5cQbLabj3U9l3tke1pg&quot;&gt;Stephen Malinowski&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jun 2016 12:00:57 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>Robert Douglass</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">67 at https://www.welltemperedclavier.org</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Fugue No 1 in C Major, BWV 846 - Four voices </title>
    <link>https://www.welltemperedclavier.org/fugue-no-1-c-major-bwv-846-four-voices</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;field field--body&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-item even&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The first fugue in the Well-Tempered Clavier is a beautiful introduction to the world of Bach&#039;s fugues. A fugue is a style of musical composition where a Theme (melody) is introduced, and then repeated in one or more other voices. This is in contrast to modern songs which have a melody, usually sung or played by one voice, chords, and rhythm. This is what the theme of this fugue looks like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.welltemperedclavier.org/sites/default/files/articles/files/fugue1_expanded.pdf_.png&quot; alt=&quot;Theme of Fugue 1 in C Major&quot; width=&quot;80%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the first section of the fugue, each of the four voices introduces the theme, starting on a different note. In this section, the theme never overlaps itself. After all four voices have entered with the theme, Bach starts making things more interesting, and voices start playing the theme so that it overlaps with other voices. When the theme entrances overlap, this is called &lt;em&gt;stretto&lt;/em&gt;. As you watch, you&#039;ll see that Bach uses stretto more and more, which heightens the tension of the piece.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The theme occurs 24 times in this fugue. That&#039;s no coincidence; there are 24 fugues in the cycle of the Well-Tempered Clavier (Book 1), two fugues for each of the twelve tonal keys -- once in major, once in minor (2 x 12 = 24). Bach loved numbers, symbolism, and symmetry, so this is very likely his way of showing that he intended to write 24 fugues altogether. See if you can hear each entrance of the fugue while you listen to Kimiko Ishizaka performing it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;853&quot; height=&quot;480&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/lGvl_94Bb_M?showinfo=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 14 Aug 2015 20:38:52 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>Robert Douglass</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">29 at https://www.welltemperedclavier.org</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Fugue No 1 in C Major, BWV 846 - VIDEO</title>
    <link>https://www.welltemperedclavier.org/bach/fugue-no-1-c-major-bwv-846-video</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;field field--body&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-item even&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;853&quot; height=&quot;480&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/qfJAiCSZgzU&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;p&gt;J.S. Bach, Fugue No 1 in C Major, BWV 846 - video by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC2zb5cQbLabj3U9l3tke1pg&quot;&gt;Stephen Malinowski&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jun 2016 12:03:38 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>Robert Douglass</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">68 at https://www.welltemperedclavier.org</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Prelude No 2 in C Minor, BWV 847</title>
    <link>https://www.welltemperedclavier.org/bach/prelude-no-2-c-minor-bwv-847</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;field field--body&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-item even&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The 2nd prelude, in C-Minor, is a dramatic, almost mechanical creation where tempo and articulation are the principal interpretive tools available to the artist. The piece has tempo indications from Bach, a rarity, in that bar 28 is marked &lt;em&gt;presto&lt;/em&gt;, bar 34 &lt;em&gt;adagio&lt;/em&gt;, and then &lt;em&gt;allegro&lt;/em&gt; in bar 35. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This video and recording were made at the Bösendorfer factory in Wiener-Neustadt, Austria, when Kimiko Ishizaka visited to choose an instrument for the Well-Tempered Clavier recording that was to take place later in the Teldex Studio. While she was there, the management of Bösendorfer invited her to try a special creation that they were just finishing - the 50,000th Bösendorfer ever manufactured. She sat down and played through the C-Minor Prelude one time, and then continued on to the Bösendorfer showroom. Fortunately for us, filmmaker Anna Osipanova was also there, with her cameraman, and they filmed the run-through, as well other scenes from the Bösendorfer factory, and made this video from the materials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;853&quot; height=&quot;480&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/-OUgvxkTwoU?showinfo=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;p&gt;
You can also listen to the version of the Prelude No. 2 that Kimiko recorded for the Open Well-Tempered Clavier project in 2014:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe style=&quot;border: 0; width: 100%; height: 42px;&quot; src=&quot;https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=1770973892/size=small/bgcol=ffffff/linkcol=0687f5/track=1310506307/transparent=true/&quot; seamless=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://music.kimiko-piano.com/album/bach-well-tempered-clavier-book-1&quot;&gt;Bach: Well-Tempered Clavier, Book 1 by Kimiko Ishizaka&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Sun, 16 Aug 2015 13:37:21 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>Robert Douglass</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">32 at https://www.welltemperedclavier.org</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Prelude in C Minor, WTC I, BWV 847 - VIDEO</title>
    <link>https://www.welltemperedclavier.org/bach/prelude-c-minor-wtc-i-bwv-847-video</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;field field--body&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-item even&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;853&quot; height=&quot;480&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Ezg68znooJ8&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;p&gt;J.S. Bach, Prelude in C minor, WTC I, BWV 847 - video by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC2zb5cQbLabj3U9l3tke1pg&quot;&gt;Stephen Malinowski&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jun 2016 12:08:53 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>Robert Douglass</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">71 at https://www.welltemperedclavier.org</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Fugue No 2 in C-Minor, BWV 847</title>
    <link>https://www.welltemperedclavier.org/bach/fugue-no-2-c-minor-bwv-847</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;field field--body&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-item even&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The C-Minor Fugue, in three voices, is textbook material for learning what a fugue really is. DaveConservatoire uses a live performance by Kimiko Ishizaka from 2013 to exemplify various fugal constructions in this video:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;853&quot; height=&quot;480&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/3tU1PDS9kyI?showinfo=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;p&gt;
You can hear the later, studio recording of the same piece in this video. It is interesting to hear how Kimiko&#039;s interpretation of the piece evolved from 2013 to 2014, over the course of constant study and multiple performances&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;853&quot; height=&quot;480&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/yrk2_pxD5Bk?showinfo=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Sun, 16 Aug 2015 13:50:10 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>Robert Douglass</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">33 at https://www.welltemperedclavier.org</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Prelude in C-Sharp Major, WTC I, BWV 848 - VIDEO</title>
    <link>https://www.welltemperedclavier.org/bach/prelude-c-sharp-major-wtc-i-bwv-848-video</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;field field--body&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-item even&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;853&quot; height=&quot;480&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/rkJ18tA9DAA&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;p&gt;J.S. Bach, Prelude in C-sharp major, WTC I, BWV 848 - video by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC2zb5cQbLabj3U9l3tke1pg&quot;&gt;Stephen Malinowski&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jun 2016 12:33:52 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>Robert Douglass</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">75 at https://www.welltemperedclavier.org</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Fugue in C-Sharp Major, WTC I, BWV 848 - VIDEO</title>
    <link>https://www.welltemperedclavier.org/bach/fugue-c-sharp-major-wtc-i-bwv-848-video</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;field field--body&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-item even&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;853&quot; height=&quot;480&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/wLNJgrTyPw8?list=PLGXthnFPaq1883C_rfnlwbCduq6wPlq1G&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 11 Jul 2016 09:26:15 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>Robert Douglass</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">78 at https://www.welltemperedclavier.org</guid>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
